<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Exploring technology one step at a time </title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/post/</link>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <author></author>
    <rights>(C) 2015</rights>
    <updated>2015-05-04 11:39:26 -0700 PDT</updated>

    
      
        <item>
          <title>linux developer ultrabook</title>
          <link>http://localhost:1313/blog/2015/05/04/linux-developer-ultrabook/</link>
          <pubDate>Mon, 04 May 2015 11:39:26 PDT</pubDate>
          <author></author>
          <guid>http://localhost:1313/blog/2015/05/04/linux-developer-ultrabook/</guid>
          <description>&lt;p&gt;For a while now I&amp;rsquo;ve wanted to move from my macbook to a linux ultrabook. And I finally decided to do something about it.
So I set out to find laptops that would give me the same things I like about my macbook but without OSX. In this adventure I end up trying 3 different machines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I looked at all the options and there are many but very few of them seemed to come close to what the macbook pro could do.
With linux you have to be a bit more careful when you pick hardware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So in the end I ended up in the section of gaming laptops and decided on the Maingear Pulse 15&amp;rdquo;.
It&amp;rsquo;s a beautiful laptop, I got to pick the case color but ordered during the harsh winter weather which caused delays in my delivery. In the end I received my laptop about 3 weeks after the original shipping date estimate. I almost cancelled my order but am really glad I didn&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine comes with 2 SSD&amp;rsquo;s in fake raid amounting up to 512GB that I&amp;rsquo;m using as my root volume. It has a 1TB spinning disk that comes with it. This is the disk I use to run dockers and VM&amp;rsquo;s of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My macbook pro is 2 years old so I knew this machine should be faster when I try compiling things. So I took one of our largest projects and started a clean compile cycle. I repeated that 10 times, on my macbook this would average between 2m and 2m30s. On the maingear this is about 30s.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        </item>
      
    

  </channel>
</rss>
